What does it mean to endure things
rightly? Is it just about patience and
gritting one's teeth within the
framework of the precepts, or is there
more to it?
Uh, well, that's how it starts.
So, you certainly shouldn't be trying to
if you're just starting out, you haven't
been keeping the precepts, you don't
really have anything to endure except
the discomfort of not breaking the
precepts. Um
Um
but uh fundamentally it is more than
that. Like it's it's
uh you're not just waiting
as if simply not doing certain things
externally is going to uh tame your mind. And it
is going to uh tame your mind. And it
may not even be uncomfortable like you
will get used to it uh pretty soon
as most monks do. and doesn't even mean
that they're practicing.
Um, so it's
what you have to endure is much more
than just
u
random pains as well. Like you're not
just seeking out things to to make
yourself experience pain. It's
when there the mind craves for something
and you don't provide it.
Pain comes up that's what you endure.
But it's not even about the pain.
It's not even that the pain is good or
something. It's simply is a symptom of
the fact that you're not giving into
something unh wholesome.
And then you
by enduring the pain like unless you can
endure the pain you will cease to
restrain that unh wholesome thing.
So that's really what the emphasis
should be in am I restraining the unh
wholesome intention that arose whether
or not it's painful and then if it's
painful I endure it but sometimes it may
not even be painful in fact eventually
it would be pleasant
um because then the mind starts to
understand that uh not going for those
things is actually the better
alternative. Um, so in terms of like
Um, so in terms of like
how do you do that then? Like how do you
uh know that you're actually restraining
an wholesome intention? Well, precisely
by not putting the emphasis on whether
it's whether it's um painful or pleasant
to uh
like whether the situation is painful or
pleasant is not to measure. It could be
extremely painful
and uh to to not do something and then
it's actually uh bad like you're
actually going the wrong way
by uh avoiding that thing like the all
the selfmortification
practices that you would read read about
in the sutras. Why? Because
those things are imposed independently
of discerning the mind's craving.
They just abstractly reasoned as oh well
if I renounce more things then I am
closer to freedom from attachments or
something. Um, but what you want to see is
Um, but what you want to see is
what are the things that my mind is
actually leaning towards. Meaning kind
of the things that
I kind of find myself being being pushed
to engage in these things whether I like
it or not. And then I can, you know, uh,
uh, secondarily say yes or say no. But
fundamentally the that that impulse was
there first.
So those are the things you you you want
to start investigating and seeing well
and you will see naturally when you
don't follow those impulses that came on
their own but you actually discern them
uh because then that's the only way that
you will be uh restraining them.
Otherwise you just uh uh doing random
observances externally but you actually
see those impulses you don't give into
them then that that uh discomfort is going to
then that that uh discomfort is going to
come up
strongly or weakly doesn't matter what
matters is you didn't give in. So
So
that happens with the precepts
obviously. Um it's just like
it's a bit simpler in the sense that you
don't really have to question your
intentions as much especially in the beginning
as much especially in the beginning
because it's pretty clear what you
shouldn't do. So for somebody who's
who's not used to even that then it's
going to just that blind keeping the
precepts is already going to uh involve
restraining their intentions. But at
some point you're not even going to have
intentions to to break the precepts. But
you're going to have other intentions
still based on craving. And if you're
not making effort to discern them, then
nothing is going to show you that
they're unh wholesome because it's not
even that you're going to be feeding
this massive uh da on account of them
that would show you that there's a
problem. Uh so that's when then you would have to
Uh so that's when then you would have to
to start seeing like well regardless of
whether it's it's um externally
prohibited or regardless of even whether
it feels uh painful when I engage in it.
I have to to start putting first the
fact that well there was an impulse
there
and the the the the going along with
those impulses in and of itself keeps
you within samsara because it means you know
within samsara because it means you know
you could have survived that one episode
could have been fine nothing bad
happened but you are training your mind
or training yourself so that
when things come up painful or painful
or pleasant, you have to act.
Uh, and it's going to be a matter of
time until
that. In fact, well, the mere the mere
if if you were to um let's say see in
hindsight, uh the mere fact of needing to act,
uh the mere fact of needing to act,
even if there are absolutely no negative
consequences on account of it
externally, the mere fact of needing to
act, that impulse
is already uh painful. It's already a
burden that you're carrying.
But obviously you've been carrying that
forever. So you don't realize it.
Uh so that's why it's an issue whatever
kind of pressure it is
uh to still be giving into it cuz you're
you're training that habit.
And uh the fact that it doesn't seem
like an issue is actually exactly how it
uh goes on indefinitely. Like nobody
just wakes up and and uh abandons
existence. um like you just get caught
up in it one way or the other.
So like the enduring things rightly is
less about let's say finding the right
method or technique or way of enduring
>> but it's more the discernment and
clarity towards
what I'm actually enduring.
>> Well yeah but even then like it's again
the point is not what
The point is not the enduring like the
enduring is a is a
is a side effect
of not do not giving into something unh
wholesome. And that's important because
uh if you put first the enduring,
you might ignore that
that very effort that you're putting
into endure this is let's say a type of
restlessness like subjecting yourself to painful
like subjecting yourself to painful
circumstances
out of some impatient uh
uh attitudes towards the practice like
you want to speed it up or something and
then you go and start fasting or
whatever out of that intention. Not that
it's uh inherently bad to to experience
uh inherently bad to to experience
difficulties and you should always try
to go the comfortable route. No, the
problem is always is why were you going
towards that? So
um
yeah, then you would be overlooking what
actually matters. If you just think that
enduring discomfort is inherently
part of the training, it's like inher
enduring discomfort is is is what goes
hand in hand
with uh not giving in to unh wholesome
uh not giving in to unh wholesome
states.
But it doesn't mean that whenever you're
enduring discomfort, you're actually not
giving into something unh wholesome.
In fact, you could even be enduring
discomfort on account of like I don't
know uh having given existential things
like uh enduring the discomfort of a
marriage or or having kids
but it will feel there will always be
discomfort if I
restrain myself from giving into the
impulses. >> Yeah. Again, it it doesn't have to be
>> Yeah. Again, it it doesn't have to be
super
>> Yeah.
course and like you're falling apart or
something. >> There's just there's a uneasiness
>> There's just there's a uneasiness
>> like it would have felt easier to to
just go with it.
>> And that's the pretty much the
definition of what an impulse is.
So there would be the uh the difference
as well between
like wrongly enduring would be still
doing the endurance as a form of
activity >> whereas and rightly enduring is like you
>> whereas and rightly enduring is like you
said the result of
>> discerning and having clarity about
fundamentally what's wholesome what's
unh wholesome.
>> Yeah. Yeah. It's like a d it becomes a
duty you take up
just blindly like I do this because it
is good by itself
and then if if if it's stops being
unpleasant then you feel like okay so what do I do
then you feel like okay so what do I do
now
and that's that's like that wasn't the
And you mentioned speeding up the
practice.
Are there any
ways or legitimate uh yeah reasons I
guess for actually speeding up the
practice or what would be a way to speed
up the practice if there is a way?
>> Well, it's it it can never be anything
you do blindly. That's for sure. Like it
can never be just a technique or method
that you do and you just apply it
verbatim and then that makes it work by itself
and then that makes it work by itself
as in like you follow this procedure
and the product is going to be assembled
and ready just because you follow the
procedure. It never works that way because the
It never works that way because the
entire training the and well suffering
as well is all based on your intentions.
So you cannot fix the issue without
actually addressing the root cause.
Uh and uh
the way to speed up the practice
actually uh then is
uh then is
look for what are the things that you
are not actually uh restraining
that are impulses.
So quite often actually uh it's it's you
would naturally gravitate to picking up
these random observances
as as like okay well if I if I uh stop
eating with a spoon
I will cuz you need that's more
uncomfortable and surely like that's
going to uh um
like yeah it's preferable to to eat with
a spoon.
versus not eating with with a spoon.
It's preferable to to wear clothes
rather than being naked. It's preferable
to eat normal food versus just eating
leaves. Therefore, surely I am giving up
craving because I am going for this more
difficult thing. But was was there an
impulse there
that you were actually like were you
obsessed about uh wearing clothes
and uh and uh eating with a spoon?
Or do you just assume that because it's
more difficult it's going to be training
your mind and then ironically simply
because you have that view you will have
impulses that you will completely
overlook and give into. So that's that's
what um the the the
Buddha and the sutas you you would see
these criticisms of these aesthetics
back in the day that they would be doing
all these inspiring uh aesthetic
practices. Uh but then they would like when
Uh but then they would like when
whenever a monk would arrive like a
Buddhist monk to see them uh it would be
like just absolutely making a racket
arguing about their views.
uh you know like just behaving like just
under strain really. Um and obviously it
doesn't have to be that way
uh in order to still you know it could
be small things
that nobody would blame you for
externally. Nobody would would think,
oh, look, he's greedy or he's averse.
But if you were honest, you would see,
oh, yeah, I do have an impulse uh for
this that I'm not really able to to
like if I didn't give into it, I would
be subject to rebellion from my own
mind. Um so those are the things that you have
Um so those are the things that you have
to it really comes down to honesty to uh
recognizing those things. Uh and then
that's how you will speed up your
practice like not making exceptions on
that level.
And yeah, almost
like very rarely
would it actually be something
very straightforward where you could
just decide, oh, I'm not going to do X
and that's it.
It's far more subtle than that most of
the time. Like it's it's a specific kind
of
habits and avenues of of
sort of finding safety that you might
have making things the way you prefer.
And the problem is like if you don't
have enough honesty, you won't even see
them cuz it's just like
it just goes through automatically
accepted. And they're probably not too
big of a deal as well that people you
would live with would point it out to
you and would say, "Well, it's not okay
to behave like that."
>> Yeah.
>> And it's not even necessarily the same
thing all the time. So, it's not like
every single day I'm doing it and like
it's just obvious.
>> Um, that's why you have to learn to pick
up the signs of your mind as described.
Um because the same way as the the king
doesn't have the same pre preferences
from day to day. You you won't even have
the same impulses from day to day. you
know, initially you will like uh
sexuality and these very coarse things
like you can just pinpoint them and be
sure like, okay, I'm still struggling
with this. But eventually it's going to
be kind of so um
indirect and so not necessarily like
hidden, but just
>> personal in a way.
>> Yeah. Personal or kind of um
circumstantial as well. Like like I it's
not even going to come up every day but
you if you were honest you would know in
this specific scenario which I may never
have experienced before
this way of acting is going along with
the impulses.
So would be
like obviously speeding up the practice
usually comes along with okay I going to
pile these additional activities
additional observances on top of each
other. >> Yeah. So restraining that as well,
>> Yeah. So restraining that as well,
>> that's that's going to be part of
speeding up your practice. Like not
acting out of See, that's a great
example actually these these uh restless
impulses that you would have to to just
pile up more things.
Uh even if again it feels completely
justified >> even mentally contemplating.
>> even mentally contemplating.
>> Exactly. Yeah. just adding like oh I'm
spend 3 hours every day contemplating
such and such
>> um because you know I read in the sutas
that this leads to so I'm just going to
and then yeah sure somebody might have
uh dedicated themselves to contemplating
that but are you doing it out of an
impulse
in which case you certainly are not
contemplating whatever it is that was actually being
whatever it is that was actually being
referred to there
because whatever it is that is actually
wholesome is
is
along the lines of sub subduing
impulses.
So that's also why uh the the practice
really begins with the right view like
when you have this reference point to
know oh this is actually an impulse
uh then you will be able to include
craving actually
rather than just kind of uh blindly
accepting it when it camouflages itself
into these kind of supposed wholesome
things
>> and would be a like a practical way of
going about it given that you are in an
environment that's you know where there
isn't any kind of course obstructions
that you you have certain activities
that are just on a day-to-day basis you
you need to do to maintain the place to
maintain yourself you know you need to
eat need to clean a few things probably
even as a lay person if you kind of live
on your own or family but you have
certain activities throughout the day
that are necessary in a way obviously
then there might be days it's raining
you cannot clean and then you will
actually might notice oh actually
there's this restlessness and I did the
cleaning all but let's say you have
these basic activities
>> but but exactly but that doesn't mean
that doesn't mean that you were always
cleaning out of that restlessness it
depends >> so see that's what I meant just now with
>> so see that's what I meant just now with
like situation just come up
>> and it doesn't necessarily have to have
any connection with anything that
happened before. So like it could be
that you just right now have an impulse
to get rid of that lack of activity
somehow and you need to see it there and then as
and you need to see it there and then as
like okay this impulse has arisen now
rather than sort of uh solidify it too
much into like okay so I'm just like
doing too much so let me take on an
observance of reducing my activities and
just doing less.
Because even if sometimes you were doing
the cleaning out of restlessness,
the fact that you just imposed it in
that blanket way means you don't know
what you're doing. So some other impulse
is going to come up and you're not going
to see it.
So it's just moving from one thing to
the other basically like a kind of like
a like a shadow like you know wherever
you cast a light now the shadow is
elsewhere.
But it doesn't have to be that way. It's
not like it's uh inherently kind of
arcane and and has so many moving parts
that it just that's why it's so hard to
to uh
succeed in training your mind. It's that
kind of
uh tendency to prioritize things that
are secondary
and not want to look at the often very
simple fact that yes there is an impulse
here. So you kind of have that tendency to to
So you kind of have that tendency to to
just uh um do anything other than sort
of stay with that ambiguous level of oh
I see that
there's just this pressure towards this
kind well not even necessarily towards a
specific thing.
It just arose that way and it kind of
looks for gratification here and there.
Um, and just seeing that as the issue,
like seeing acting out of that as the
issue, not oh, but how many times a day
I end up uh cleaning or how many hours a
day I spend cleaning, it's much easier
to just kind of cuz then you can you can
um
get a lot more certainty and say, "Okay,
so now from now onwards, if I just limit
my cleaning to 1 hour a day, I'll be
fine." Cuz then you won't have to think
about it next time. you won't have to
see what impulse is there next time.
So, it's kind of like everybody has that
like you already want to know what
you're going to do ahead
and it just doesn't work that way
because the the impulses the direction
of the impulses is going to change.
So it's like you have a fog
such that you can only see ahead of you
like one meter and you have to accept
that like whatever map you think you have of
like whatever map you think you have of
what's going to come after it's not it's
wrong. You have to make decisions based on like
You have to make decisions based on like
what what's right ahead of you.
It's like your your sense of urgency is
getting in your way.
Well, it's a misdirected sense of
urgency. So, because the sense of urgency leads
So, because the sense of urgency leads
to uh like effort, faith,
um all of those are factors
of awakening or things that lead to
awakening if you have the right view. In
other words, you know what it is that
you have to do.
Um because yeah sense of urgency can be
imagine like how many wrong views you
could pick up with a sense of urgency. Um so
Um so
that's why it's it's yes it's it's it's
good to have a sense of urgency and you
need to have it otherwise you won't um
be going against the grain as as the
Buddha said. Um but uh it needs to be
informed. It needs to be redirected
and it's like yeah if I feel impatient
and I feel like I'm not going fast
enough with my practice
uh that's fine. It doesn't mean you need
to kind of like um deny it and say no
you know it's it's good enough or
something like no maybe you are lacking
in some respects.
Uh but uh you have to keep in mind like
it doesn't even necessarily like you
you're not going to get anything of
value by
analyzing things in this kind of
uh abstract way is like kind of as if
there is some specific action that I
just have to stop or some specific
behavior that I just have to say no to
forever except the precepts of course,
but we're assuming that that's covered.
Um, and you have to be ready that no, it's
and you have to be ready that no, it's
it's it's really just I have to be
vigilant for completely new things that I've
for completely new things that I've
never encountered before.
And that's going to be more accurate
than if you than than thinking like, oh,
it's this it's just these
I can just make a determination and then
assume that everything that comes after
is going to be covered.
So you're like you're facing each day
and you're making you're making your
decisions based on what impulses have I
am I discerning right now.
Is the sense of urgency
sort of problematic because it does it
because it comes with a a pressure that
you can't endure?
>> Well, no. It's not the sense of urgency
that's problematic like
>> uh cuz you you need to have it in order
to to practice. Even
>> Yeah. Even the like the craving but it
said craving is overcome by means of
craving. >> So
there is going to be a pressure behind
it
but like I said it it matters
what you do on account of that pressure.
It's not all on the same level.
So you can have a sense of urgency and
you can decide to
do 1,000 frustrations
>> to diminish your conceit.
Or that's a very coarse example
obviously but just to illustrate the
principle. Uh or you can look more
closely at uh
when you speak, why are you speaking?
Like what are your motivations for
speech?
Not like oh I I I should speak less
automatically and I should just take a vow of silence.
the the pressure of the sense of urgency
is that different from
the [clears throat] you know you just
take another precepts and now you're
calming down within you know that
pressure that you get when you first
take on the precepts and it's like
>> obviously then you just want to put out
the fire
>> well the sense of urgency is what would
have led you to take the take on the
precepts like if you didn't feel like
you you were
>> under some kind of threat.
>> Mhm. you wouldn't have done such an
unnatural thing
which was certainly at least in the
beginning it wasn't natural.
So
it's not even like for example see you
could even say oh okay so I shouldn't
have a sense of urgency
uh which again it's like you remove
or you try to remove
the opportunity for problems to arise
rather than just removing the problems
which is always going to fail because as
long as you exist there is going to be
the opportunity for problems for
defilements will arise. So sense of
frequency isn't the issue.
It's obviously something that can result
in uh kind of misdirection, but it's not
the issue in and of itself. It's
basically the fact that when you have
the sense of urgency, it comes up.
Um
you let it overly proliferate
into just a blind restlessness.
But as a as a just a call to action,
it could very well be, oh, actually I
should restrain my restlessness. And you
would be doing that out of a sense of
urgency. So you could actually realize, okay, I
So you could actually realize, okay, I
need to practice. Uh, I'm not doing
enough. And then realize,
oh, actually, uh, that's true. I haven't
been doing enough. Right now I have this
this pressure to
I don't know uh
just start saying no to something
that I'm that is not even always unh
wholesome but like I just feel that if I just
but like I just feel that if I just
remove this
I'll be kind of uh somehow getting ahead
and then you realize well but this is
clearly coming out of that impulse.
So I have a sense of urgency that I
should be freeing myself from craving.
That's right. That
it's right there.
And then you will need the sense of
urgency to stick to that because it's
not going to happen automatically. You
you you let your guard down and then
something else is going to come up and
you will act out of it. So that's why uh
the whole thing of like oh you you
abstain from [snorts]
these um
restless activities activities based on
craving. Uh many times can sound to
people as if okay so
that just means you don't do anything
basically. But the thing is uh
or or you or there's no need for effort.
It's all just passive.
>> Your body just happens.
>> Yeah. Um but uh
I mean this to describe it all the time.
It will take effort
like see if it if it was easier
to stick to that middle way and uh
neither indulge nor go for these blind
observances then you wouldn't need the Buddha.
then you wouldn't need the Buddha.
It would just be natural for everybody
to already be doing it.
Uh but you will need effort to pull
yourself back from both of those
directions. >> And actually you don't need effort
>> And actually you don't need effort
of that right kind to go for one of the
two cuz it's what your mind wants
anyway. Like as I said those impulses
you kind of find them there already.
So even if it feels like effort
like when let's say when you really want
to do something when there's a project
that you really want to complete
and then you spend days and nights like
not sleeping or whatever
and then uh you might think okay yeah
this requires effort. Well, sure in a
worldly sense, but the effort of the
practice, the effort that leads to
awakening is like when it's not actually
something that you have an impulse for
because otherwise it cannot be nibbana.
Nibbana is a sensation of impulses.
So you you don't arrive at that
magically [snorts]
by giving into impulses.